Richard B. Talbot Papers, 1967-1994
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Richard B. Talbot Papers, 1967-1994
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1995-024
2 boxes; 1.4 cu. ft.
The collection consists primarily of speeches, speech resource and research materials, administrative notes, departmental program planning and budgeting materials.
Richard B. Talbot
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Richard B. Talbot Papers were donated to Special Collections in 1994.
Biographical/Historical Information
Dr. Richard B. Talbot was professor, Biomedical Sciences and Veterinary Medical Informatics at Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg. He also served as a consultant in the areas of veterinary medical regulatory and governmental affairs, veterinary informatics, and veterinary medical pharmacology and toxicology.
Richard Talbot was born and reared in Marshall County, Kansas. He attended Kansas State University where he was awarded baccalaureate and doctor of veterinary medicine degrees. He later obtained a Ph.D. degree from Iowa State Unversity.
Talbot also was a faculty member at Iowa State University and the University of Georgia. He started at Iowa State as an instructor of physiology and moved through the ranks to associate professor. At the University of Georgia, he served as professor, as chairman of the Department of Physiology and Pharmacology, as director of the Institute for Comparative Medicine, and as dean of the College of Veterinary Medicine.
Dr. Talbot came to Virginia Tech from the University of Georgia in 1975 to help the university plan and develop the Virginia/Maryland Regional College of Veterinary Medicine. He served as dean of the college until the first class was graduated in 1984. From 1984 until October of 1987 he was devoted full-time to research and teaching. For the next two years, he served as director of the Office of New Animal Drug Evaluation at the U. S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) while on leave from Virginia Tech. At the FDA, a part of Talbot's work was the oversight of evaluation for new animal drug entities requesting approval to market in the United States. Other initiatives included the management of new drug applications using electronic submissions, and the creation of procedures to implement the Generic Animal Drug and Patent Restoration Act. Talbot returned to teaching and research in November of 1989. His research interests involved veterinary medical informatics and included:
Management and retrieval of pharmacological and toxicological information
Management and retrieval of national and international regulatory information
Veterinary medical manpower predictive models
Economic aspects of veterinary medical delivery systems
His work was funded by the FDA and the U. S. Department of Agriculture (USDA) to develop an information base on potential drug residues in food products of animal origin. He also worked in the areas of pharmacologic and toxicologic effects of the stable rare earth compounds.
Talbot was a consultant to several universities and pharmaceutical companies, to the National Institutes of Health, the Bureau of Health Manpower, the FDA, the USDA, and Hazelton Laboratories Corporation. He served on the National Academy of Sciences National Research Council Committee on Veterinary Medical Sciences. He served as editor-in-chief of the Journal of Veterinary Medical Education, as president-elect of the American Veterinary Computer Society, and chairman of the American Veterinary Medical Association's Committee on Informatics. He was editor of Veterinary Pharmaceuticals and Biologicals, a standard reference work for veterinary medicine.
Dr. Talbot's activities also included service on the Board of Directors of Hazelton Corporation, a life sciences corporation, and First Virginia Bank of the Southwest. He was a member and president-elect of the Rotary Club of Blacksburg, Virginia, and an elder in the Presbyterian Church.
Scope and Content
The collection consists primarily of speeches, speech resource and research materials, administrative notes, departmental program planning and budgeting materials. Speech resources folders are organized chronologically, with undated items first followed by dated items.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged chronologically. Please note: Folder numbers in Box 2 continue the numbering sequence from Box 1.
Contents List
- Speeches, 1967. (Box-folder 1:1)
- Speeches, 1968. (Box-folder 1:2)
- Speeches, 1969. (Box-folder 1:3)
- Speeches, 1970. (Box-folder 1:4)
- Speeches, 1971. (Box-folder 1:5)
- Speeches, 1972. (Box-folder 1:6)
- Speeches, 1973. (Box-folder 1:7)
- Speeches, 1974. (Box-folder 1:8)
- Speeches, 1975. (Box-folder 1:9)
- Speeches, 1976. (Box-folder 1:10)
- Speeches, 1977. (Box-folder 1:11)
- Speeches, 1978. (Box-folder 1:12)
- Speeches, 1979. (Box-folder 1:13)
- Speeches, 1980. (Box-folder 1:14)
- Speeches, 1981. (Box-folder 1:15)
- Speeches, 1982. (Box-folder 1:16)
- Speeches, 1984. (Box-folder 1:17)
- Speeches, undated. (Box-folder 1:18)
- Speech resources 1. (Box-folder 1:19)
- Speech resources 2. (Box-folder 1:20)
- Speech resources 3. (Box-folder 1:21)
- Speech resources 4. (Box-folder 1:22)
- Speech resources 5. (Box-folder 1:23)
- Veterinary Medical Informatics. (Box-folder 1:24)
- Departmental Program Planning and Budgeting 1: Anatomy & Histology, Avian Medicine. (Box-folder 1:25)
- Departmental Program Planning and Budgeting 2: Medical Microbiology. (Box-folder 1:26)
- Departmental Program Planning and Budgeting 3: Medicine & Surgery. (Box-folder 1:27)
- Departmental Program Planning and Budgeting 4: Pathology, Parisitology, Physiology & Pharmacology, Diagnostic Laboratories. (Box-folder 1:28)
- Model Budget: VMRCVM Budget. (Box-folder 1:29)
- Model Budget: Cost Center Budgets. (Box-folder 1:30)
- Model Budget: Miscellaneous (expenditures, revenues, salaries, enrollment, start-up comparison). (Box-folder 1:31)
- Correspondence. (Box-folder 1:32)
- Physiology of Aging 1. (Box-folder 1:33)
- Physiology of Aging 2. (Box-folder 1:34)
- "The View from Here," article about Dr. Talbot by Warren Strother. (Box-folder 1:35)
- "The Behavior of Certain Lanthanons in Rats" by Goran Magnusson (Box-folder 1:36)
- "Quality and Equality in Helath Professions Education and Service" by Lloyd C. Elam (Box-folder 1:37)
- "The Book of Life" by Robert L. Sinsheimer (Box-folder 1:38)
- Administrative notes: Administrative Development. (Box-folder 1:39)
- Administrative notes: Faculty Effort and Faculty Retention. (Box-folder 1:40)
- Administrative notes: Program Development I-V (Instruction, Physical Plant, Financial Resources, Teaching Hospital, Research & Graduate Programs). (Box-folder 1:41)
- Administrative notes: Program Development VI-X (Support Services, Organization & Administration, Personnel Development, Intercollegiate & Extramural Relations, Public Service Extension). (Box-folder 1:42)
- History of the AVMA. (Box-folder 1:43)
- Biographical materials. (Box-folder 1:44)
- Miscellaneous materials. (Box-folder 1:45)
- Paperweight from dedication of Richard B. Talbot Educational Resources Center. (Box-folder 1:46)
- Title pages of reprints pulled from collection. (Box-folder 2:47)
- Title pages of reprints pulled from collection. (Box-folder 2:48)
- Conference presentations. (Box-folder 2:49)
- Appraisal of the Safety of Chemicals in Foods, Drugs, and Cosmetics. (Box-folder 2:50)
- Slides. (Box-folder 2:51)
- Documents from Dr. Talbot's files--sources unknown. (Box-folder 2:52)
- Documents from Dr. Talbot's files--sources unknown. (Box-folder 2:53)
- Documents from Dr. Talbot's files--journals not available in Addison. (Box-folder 2:54)
- Documents from Dr. Talbot's files--journals not available in Addison. (Box-folder 2:55)
- Documents from Dr. Talbot's files--journals not available in Addison. (Box-folder 2:56)
- Documents from Dr. Talbot's files--journals not available in Addison. (Box-folder 2:57)